hi all good evening guys am i audible and visible give me thumbs up if you can hear
me out great so so how's preparation going on guys like how we preparing for contest
all going good
okay great let me share my screen
do let me know guys if you can see the screen share good so
fine let's pull ipad
okay kabe i will talk about that you will get to an understanding on that point okay
need not to worry i'll explain that point okay i'll speak on that today
ipad sharing is also working fine right so kabe can you add this as a question at last
a moment of the class at last whether this question is answered if you understand by
that time or let me know that if not we'll pick it up okay
so guys any updates anything there okay okay you fix a timer uh great so much let's look
at this
also you i had a code to
set timer nice let's i set up the timer guys uh we'll set up for five minutes uh and i'll
say start okay it works fine great so guys any updates anything going on your life or
how's preparation going any updates on assignments let me check what's the percentages of our
batch how many people are able to solve things i haven't checked in some time back
so one quick feedback i need are you able to follow up with my teachings are you enjoying
it uh like do i need to work on anything or from the topics point of view if you have
any challenge understanding it do let me know okay then and there itself so that we
clear them out and then we move ahead step by step okay guys uh
so our assignments this percentage is 38 how to add a slider uh where you want to add
a slider uh somewhere just wanted to know that a slide of a what like uh i didn't get
your complete question summit maybe if you are typing it that's good uh like an option
slide through different things as in there will be two things clicking on one thing will show a
page on the other okay it's kind of a toggle rendering content based on html like toggling
the content right on a button right or like a image carousel like moving one after the other
okay that thing uh it's a button based event like enabling a div and disabling a div
uh so that is something that you can do as of now but uh like if you want it more dynamic
you have to go for react but current for current knowledge it's like if you are rendering one part
of html then uh depending on a button click or event or a you know swipe event you have to
check which is event is like actually working as a swipe okay or generally in uh web browsers you
don't have a spike you can have that in the mobile events so you have to check like uh then
once that is there and how do you render the other part of the content so it just that you know
toggling between two different ifs one different one day will have the current content and the
next day so uh there is a okay if there is a default html or not uh there might not be a
default html built for that but we can you know uh in react based components you'll find it
there you will find it okay
okay revision i'll do that from okay toggling through different text uh good
so
again this is a new addition this is a great thing uh so you added a background image isn't it
on this application
whatever you do okay you are also okay this is nice this feature is nice you are uh changing the
sentences after each second or what timeline you are using it
so quotes.js is a different file uh you have an array of items uh then this you are using this
array
500 milliseconds is it
after six seconds every six seconds okay
great one you are trying to apply the knowledge we have learned up to greater extent so
really happy with your application somewhere this add on you know inspiration for the people in our
class or the batches will be i'll be talking about this one in the upcoming batches but great
so guys uh can we get started with today's class can anyone drop uh in whatsapp group
like we are able to get started uh one message would really help us you know i see a few people
joining after the message
so
okay great so let's do one thing
uh there's a message dropped i'll check from my side
yeah great thank you brahmod
okay thank you shik uh now so firstly just want to know like if you have any doubts from previous
class where we started with this operator we understood context of this and what this talks
about like we have figured out that you know this is always referring to some object
object and on top level we had only four types of objects one is empty object then one is window
one is global and the object itself which you are calling on right and there is something is
undefined key these are the possible values we have seen and when it comes to this node.js
this is specific and when it comes to windows this is specific to browser
right and there's a thumb rule simple console log in node.js will always give empty
whereas in window like one browser you will get a window object by default and other keys are like
if there are no context in strict mode specifically you will see only in strict
mode you'll see the undefined coming up in other cases you might not be seeing and we also understood
what is strict versus non-strict mode whereas strict mode uh you know applies few more rules
than existing javascript in it was introduced in es5 version where they introduced this one which
had more error handling better error handling and exception handling that we have seen
after this once we understood this this operator then we went went on ahead to
understand something called as constructor function
so these are the two topics that we have discussed last class and when it comes to
constructor functions we figured out that hey if you want to create an object one of the way is
always open a curly place and write down the different types of data types or the custom
data type whatever you want to build that's all cool but what if i want to build a same sort of
objects multiple times let's say this is the same object the content is still same like if the if
that is a use case how can we automate it so the other way around of creating objects we figure out
is constructor functions where you define a function uh function which starts again the function
name should start with the capital letter let's say i say fun and this fun may be returning you a
new object so here inside this one you have a constructor you define a constructor sorry
you don't need a constructor you can directly simply define all the content that you wanted
using the this key like simply let's say context so this start all the variables
and whatever values are the parameters you accept here you define a parameter and using this if this
is used for initializing all the variables and if you want to create a new object always you have
to call a new keyword this new keyword is generally working as a memory assignment which creates a
memory
okay and the this memory is loaded with this variables whatever you pass in here
and it is stored in some let's say variable here and this variable acts as a reference key
right so this is something we have understood in last class uh any doubts still now guys on
this concepts just revised the context we have understood in last class just want to know if you
are facing any challenge or understood like this one if everything is clear can you give
me a thumbs up so that we can get started with today's class
great so if you see from the last class whatever we thought to cover in oops we have reached to a
place where we have to discuss something called as classes and classical inheritance
so I would request right uh one thing is that JS is a more of a functional programming language
but as you see that there was a too much growth of OOPS system object-oriented system
of OOPS system object-oriented system because of this growth this ECMAS script team like in ES6
they launched a better version or a neater version of describing constructor functions
and better way of doing or implementing constructor function is using classes
this was introduced in ES6 now let's see like if both are solid like uh one thing I want to highlight
is constructor function and classes are doing the same thing one is the older way of writing it
uh still people prefer this way in many places and some people prefer this way so it is up to
the use case this thing was introduced only because like popularity and people how they use
and people how they use they wanted to introduce classes and we'll come to that classes
okay one thing a few things that I want to set uh you know give you highlights on is that you know
the object-oriented programming that you see in Java or C++ is not same as in JS
JS uh you know they just added some support for the classes but it doesn't work in the same way
we'll see why why not what all things are there here okay now let's get started with uh classes
guys now uh so first and foremost thing you know whenever you go for any programming language what
is the definition that you keep hearing for class anyone what is the definition that you think in
terms of class like whenever you say class or if you go for struct if you are from C++ background
if you think okay blueprint right now how many of you understand something called blueprint
a keyword a normal word blueprint how many of you understand normal word blueprint
okay I'm not asking for class but a blueprint now okay let's see that what happens now I want to
explain one of the problem statement uh let's say if you are building societies like you so
societies you see in Hyderabad they are upper now my home like many are there uh big construction
companies real estate companies who are building societies now when you build up uh you know huge
society in each society will have 10 plus towers okay in all those 10 plus stars you might have
like you know a 2 BHK flat a 3 BHK flat a 1 BHK flat and but when you see a brochure
let's say you have a brochure when you see a brochure do you get whole map of the society
or do you get a sample blueprint of each flat
to get a simple blueprint of each flat in the brochure or do you get a whole
thing in the society blueprint right now now using that one blueprint one blueprint that they gave
you there's something architects might have uh in-depth blueprint using that one blueprint of a
one flat or maybe a 2 BHK or maybe 3 BHK he builds more than 100 houses right 100 to 200 houses
do you agree with me using one architecture or map he keep on building one after the other of same
sizes same flats guys how many of you agree i see only one thumbs of you people reacting i want to
you know see if everyone is able to follow me up okay now this blueprint whatever blueprint you
create right one blueprint is called as a class and this 100 are called as objects
okay this again goes back to the same definition if you see when we told that when we when we
decided to go for constructor function is that when you have a common variables or data types
if you want don't want to do it general duplication using this object so use one
constructor function which will create n number of objects like what do we exactly mean by that
sentence like if you have the same blueprint for n objects with only changing the variable types
like only the numbers are changing then you can go for constructor function this is still you know
again a constructor function
is still the same as a class and objects are real time objects that you create
okay so both things both this are solving the same problem now let's see one of the example of
syntaxes like how this works okay
let me create a class 22
let's say i say class dot j s
let's say class hyphen dot j s okay here now i'll introduce i'll talk about few syntaxes that how
you can declare a class now for declaring a class you have to use a keyword class then you have to
tell like what class name is let's say creating a class called person once you have this person
what you can do it inside this is like you can have a constructor now as i told you in last class
you can have a constructor now as i told you in last class that constructor is used to only
initialize the variables but not to create an object now inside this constructor let's say i
have three variables let's say i say that this dot name it means that i'm having a variable name
this is the same name i'll receive it here let's say name and age and let's say gender we have
three things okay let's say i'm assigning those variables this name dot age then let's say this
okay now this is the same syntax now let's say i try to create an object one of the way to
create an object is let's say this is a person one again you use a new keyword so you're trying to
get an access to this per class and you you don't just call this as a function
because you're just this is in a way classes are can be invoked this way when you're trying to
create an object now whenever first thing that if you see whenever we are calling this way it is
trying to actually interact with this thing at runtime whenever whatever you pass here inside
this it will be received inside this because this is the first method which will be now these are
things which are inside the classes are called methods now this method will be invoked this
constructive method now let's say if you want to pass a name like just say john
and let's say john ages maybe 26 and let's say gender is male okay once you do let's
say create another person person two new person
let's say duncan say 28
say again male okay so is the syntax clear guys how this thing works let's me
show you console logging this thing both like what class does for us same thing whatever
constructor function was doing for us same thing class is doing it just in a better way like what
do you want you can be able to relate if someone is coming from the background of this one like
object-oriented background let's say if i execute if you see i'm still able to access this person
one even you can access the object same way like let's say this is an object that you receive if
you want to access let's say i say that name then i say that person one dot age
and percent one say percent two dots and let me do update this person to
save it let me re-execute it if you see i'm getting the duncan like you know 28 and male
because it's the same way like you're accessing object you can access all the variables from it
that's good that's good now let's say i go on implementing one more version of this one let's
say call it as a let's say i call it as person one now here let's say i'm trying to add our
one method say that greeting but before going ahead this one with this one hope i hope everyone
is able to follow up with the syntax any doubts guys just one final check this is pretty basic
simple straightforward if you have any doubts at any moment give me a thumbs down or give me
some hint that that will act like i think i need to re-explain it okay let's say i'm adding a
function here functions is let's say i say that hey console dot log
i say greetings let's say i add greetings from
this dot name now let's say if i try to implement the same thing let's say i
take this object i say person hyphen one one now here instead of person object i'll use person one
and i'll do console dot log person one one now let's say if i console log if you see
in that object i'm still having all the types of data types it is still working like the same
the way you create an object with a parenthesis symbol everything you can define it inside the
constructor method itself even the functions you can declare it now let's say if i want to
access that function itself what i can do let's say i can say that function dot greeting and i
can execute that function let's say if i do that okay if you see i'm getting greetings from the
john this is printed now this is the second version that i wanted to show you guys now there
is a version three that i want to talk about where i'll take this one i'll paste it here again i'll
say that function two percent two where i'll pull this one out let's say i'll pull this one out i'll
end this i'll declare greeting here and let's say i try to still do the same console login
okay once we do this let's say again i have the same line
which i say person one two and instead of this object let's say i initialize this here
now let's say i execute this one
once i execute it now if you see i'm still getting the greetings from the john i'm still getting
from the critics from the john but i just want you to think like what could be the difference
between this version and this version where you are declaring this method inside a constructor
inside a constructor which is declaring method outside the constructor
anything nice do can you think of anything like what why undefined there i'm not exactly sure
why that undefined is coming from but there's nothing as such we are printing
you can ignore that it won't come in the browser okay if i try to execute this one let's say
if i let's say i pick this example
nothing as such like that's undefined yeah i'm getting greeting from the john but
line number 13 is giving me undefined even if i try to execute this one
let's say
i'm having person one then i'm greeting function so i'm executing it so it's it's
executing only once then i'm not sure why that undefined is coming it is printing rightfully
okay so i'll come with an explanation for that one but the main question guys here is that
i just wanted to figure out what can be the difference between
declaring this greeting function inside a constructor towards declaring the function
outside the constructor can you guys think of anything like wow what can be the reason here
or what is the magic is happening why both things are working as you know expected
okay any guesses guys any anyone can even think of anything here
i'm still able to access person one two dot greeting person one one dot greeting
i'm able to print like greeting from the john and let's say i say this as a john smith
again i execute it now if you see i'm able to print a greeting from the john smith and john both
things any ideas guys what can be the difference between these two things
if you don't know you can give me a thumbs down at that any moment right
so i see three people four people great now so but do you understand the syntax that you can
declare functions in both ways one thing in the constructor the other one is outside the
constructor both things are called as methods now and both can be used but you have to figure it
out let's say now if i have to build of like as i told you earlier that let's say i create another
file called class two dot js let's say if i want to replicate each step each of this file using a
functional like constructor functional logic let's say all the versions now let's say this
version if we want to replicate this version you will try to you'll try will understand this how
what is the difference between declaring inside a constructor versus outside
let me go back to that step by step let's see if i want to declare this person firstly
what i can do is that let's say i can create a function i can say a person
inside this i can have a multiple variables like name age and gender right
and once i have this uh anyways i can copy this and this is the version one isn't it
guys these both things are same isn't it class person and person class function person now let's
say if i go to the person one version if i go to this person one person one name age this one
this one let's i copy this again i try to print it in order to show this right whether how
this is working or not i'll try to console log and show it to you
uh let's say i am here i say person then uh person one is greeting then also i'll have
an another object from this one let's say
let's say i try to save it uh and execute this one
clear node class hyphen two dot js okay person one one is not defined okay
i should clear this and i should execute it now if you see i'm still able to execute as expected
dunkin from the main dunkin 28 meal because this is what happened past here for the person two and
i'm able to execute greeting from the john so this is working as expected as of now but i will show
you one thing is that let's say if i try to copy this particular version one from the class point
of view let's say i try to
let's say i just copy till here i just copy till here and let's say i go back here and i try to
paste this code just look at this guys what i'm doing i'm just placing that person one version
where i'm just creating a greeting inside it and then let's say i uh paste it uh and i say that
person one one one i try to accept access it now when i'm doing it one of the thing that i want to
see you is that if you see here greeting is present inside the object okay just notice this one that
greeting is inside this object itself or default object now let's say if i go to the next person
like this person person one two let's say i take this code and i try to paste it again here
once i paste it then if i access person one two now here when i expand it do you see greeting here
in person two
no right but if i try to access let's say if i try to access person one two dot greeting
and i try to call it say do you see this i'm getting greetings from john smith though it is
not present we are getting it from somewhere that is the difference between both the functions
like how we are able to access this greeting where this greetings is stored when you go for
the syntax uh like how this is working like where this is particular thing when i declared inside
this is particular thing when i declared inside on constructor function i'm in constructor or
method this was there like earlier example if you go and check here when i was doing this
this thing was present like inside this object itself like person one you see this greetings
is there but when i print person two there is no greeting so guys is the difference is
you are able to understand there's a difference when you declare inside a constructor and when
you declare outside of constructor okay i hope you are able to identify the difference i'll come
to what is happening behind the scenes in some time but i just need few more thumbs up if you
are able to figure out the difference okay now let's let's go and try to figure it out what
happening now i'll explore open this one more object if you see here there's an object attached
to the person to there's something called prototype object now if i expand this prototype object
do you see greeting present here
so this greeting is coming from this part now let's understand what happened here what happened just
okay how we were able to achieve or what is this prototype or what is happening
okay so one sort of definition that i want to give you these are what prototype is in javascript
but i'll explain this completely in depth in next class what prototype and prototypical chain
but on top level like when you declare let's say when you declare
when you declare
method inside our class
outside constructor function
that method is added into
prototype object
okay this is the sentence you do remember it guys just a basic difference now i'll
talk about this like how can you build this in the construct like using a simple constructor
function that we see if i try to avoid the classes now let's say if you see this example
if i want to replicate it this thing we know that this version person one is working fine
everything is working fine let's say if i go and say that person function percent two and i try to
copy paste this existing thing that i have and now what if i want to add something into the
prototype now if you see if i come here on the percent two i can do something like percent two
dot prototype when i try to execute this prototype you can see this is a greeting printed coming
so if i want to do the same behavior to be built in the functional programming like using
constructor function i have to do something like let's say i try to create a let's say well
let's say i try to create a let's say well i have an object called
let's say we can do this way person three
new person
say again uh let me copy this content
okay this is what it still looks like a version one of the person function but now if i want to add
a do player on something i have to do like person one dot prototype on this prototype object
i have to add greetings function if i want to execute or let it work as expected now let's say
let it work as expected now let's say if i go it do do it here i write down the same console log
and let's say i say that
console log or let's say i say that person three dot greeting
and i execute it let's see if this is working
now i'll come to the syntaxes and all the things how this is working and why this is working
let's say i go it here i try to print now cannot set properties of undefined greeting now
pardon me guys let me create on a person two
two
i try to put it onto the top i was creating it on object
okay uh
it's not a function
just a second guys
okay
why this isn't working let's say if i try to let's say we copy this person two
and let's say okay i'm creating an object on person so that's a mistake guys
guys
clear if you see i'm still able to print greetings from the john now the difference what happening
here what just prototype is where this is coming from why this is happening so the thing that i
want to say that whenever you create any object anything or whenever you create any object or
anything right always in javascript there is something called as a prototype attached to it
anything that you create which is having a memory you will always see other than primitives
other than primitives whatever you create everything will have a prototype object
a prototype object attached to it
okay now even if you create an array you will see a prototype available if you create an object
you will see a prototype available if you create a function you will see a prototype available
so anything you create this prototype will be there now why this is there what it is doing
we'll discuss in next class when we pick up prototype chain and everything but i hope you
are able to understand like how uh this thing is working like there is a difference when you create
inside a constructor when you create in the outside the constructor and how what is it like
if you see when i create an outside the constructor how this is being added no way this is added into
prototype object if you want to replicate that same behavior if you want to replicate that same
behavior in a functional constructive way you have to add it to that particular function to its
prototype that same greeting method is this clear guys are you able to understand the three
versions of it you even with the functional programming and the class level understanding
if there is anyone whom i confused do let me know
and there is a one of the thing that i want to show you there's a one of the thing that i want
to show you let's say i have here one thing i'll do is that
do you remember what type of uh used to do when we used to use type of
used to tell which type of data type right now let's say if i do percent two
do
now do you see it is returning me function though something that person to be here created is class
do you see this even if i open this person one type of
it still returns me function so one thing that i want to say it in in javascript terms right
there's nothing like class or anything these are like you know new syntax is added but behind the
scenes everything working is constructor function itself this is the logic which is being you know
built back this is the same logic which is being built back from this understanding this is
converted into this thing and then this is what built i hope that logic is clear because even
if i try to say what is the type of this person it is returning me function
okay so are you able to understand that
uh i see only one thumbs up few guys like i hope uh i'm able to make sense that okay now
so what i was saying is that in javascript there is nothing like actually classes or there is no
extra sort of logics have been added this is just so you can say syntactic sugar that is
added onto the functional constructor how can you verify that one is if i try to see
what is the data type of this class what is the data type of class if you see i'm trying to print
what is the data type using a type of operator whenever i use type of operator it generally
tells us what is our data type now when i'm checking for this person to in person one
where i am trying to execute here using the classes uh you know syntax it says that it is
a function data is a type of function so this is what i meant that hey whenever i'm even defining
a class with syntaxes or using a constructor function in an older way which is uh before esx
both are same thing this is being converted into this sort of syntax behind the scenes and this
has been loaded into the machine i hope that is that is making the sense that point
and which is better it's up to you whichever thing you use after this class after this class
till our whole month stack completes end to end we are never going to write the syntax
will be never be using classes so now by default you may understand like which is more important
and better because this is not solving any new use case like i have to i don't go to it because
you know why should i learn something new way of writing a code when whole js is a functional
programming okay the concepts now then there is one more thing that i want to talk about
like how many of you understand this you know access modifiers this keyword have you guys
came across this keyword access modifiers
i see two thumbs up guys people who gave me thumbs up can they say what
the access modifier is about okay public private
protector
so this is actually oops level of understanding where you can make a
you know methods and variables which are declared inside a class like how do you want to protect
whether it's a private variable or protected available public variable
but in javascript this doesn't exist everything is public by default so the access modifier
concept doesn't apply in js i hope that point is clear guys
no worries okay so there is no access modifier now once there are no access modifier does it
make sense to have setters and getters in a class
when there is no private variables does it do we need setters and getters
they exist but not needed you if you want to let's say if you want to update any variable let's
say if i go and say that hey let's say i got this greeting now i'll say that person one two
dot name i can say that update it as uttam sharma let's say this is working
again opening the terminal let's say i go back to this class 22 once i try to execute it
one dot js now if you see i updated it but i didn't print it again let me print this object
clear now if you see i am able to update the variable name i'll come to that munishwara
again like one thing i just want to talk about is like do you see this i'm able to update the
name again once the object is created directly using the equal to operator is this syntax clear
like this is something we should do with objects firstly and if i want to access my name again
can i do the same thing like person one two dot name so this is something like we are still like
even if you create an object you still have in permissions to update the existing content and to
read the existing content okay but whereas when you go for this you know what the setters get
us to is like whatever variables you declare inside the class let's say inside the class
let's say inside the class you have
you have person class you have name age right let's say these are the two fields available
you know what used to happen in other groups languages they used to make these variables
private let's say a private name private age okay so whenever you're trying to let's say you have
an object called person one person one object is there now you created using new person
okay earlier if you want to access these names right let's say person one dot name
or anything like you if you want to do it this way there was no output like you were not able
to access this keyword in other programming languages because these variables were not
in other programming languages because these variables were declared private
whenever we say that private it means that you cannot access the values outside it okay now
whenever we are trying to do it this is something like we are trying to read it when we say that we
are reading it we mean to say that getting the value like get name so what they used to do is
in that in the inside this class they used to write two functions what those functions are like
let's say they used to give that let's say get name and the function syntax would be like a return
this dot name
okay and if you want to update it used to have set name and this function used to take the name
updated name right used to return
the start name
also before returning it it used to update it this start name equal to name
okay these are the two works that setter and getter used to do because if you cannot access like
the the way we were doing it here was like just we are getting an object and we are giving that
variable and we are updating it directly this sort of syntax may not be happening in few
languages but in javascript you can read it directly since there is no something like
private public protected so there is no use case of having this getters and setters but they have
introduced you like setters and getters this works in the same way even without setters and getters
you will be still be using it like still be accessing the values this way itself
like still be accessing the values this way itself and read it this way
this is clear guys like i mean i'm just saying that and you don't need to actually use setters
and getters i was giving explanation for that thing that javascript doesn't really need it
if you want to update or read any variables and there are no access modifiers i hope this
thing makes sense that javascript is pretty simple this works same as a functional programming
and most of the concepts that you see are not been applicable in here okay now
next comes one of the more one of the most you know core concept let's say i create
another file called let's say class hyphen 3.js let's say i create a function
called let's again i create a person now in this person what i do is like let's say again i have
that constructor name age to our variables inside this let's say again still updated
okay this person is there fine here also i'll also do something like greet
greet
so this is a greet function where we try to console dot log greeting
from the start name let's say this is a simple syntax that i have just everything is accessible
in chairs right somewhere because everything is public you can access you can update do good
anything okay now once we have this class person inside this now if i let's say if there is a
student let's say if there is if i want to create a student object let's say i want to
create a student object do you think student will also have the name and age properties
yes you do think the student will also have a name and age right so whenever you have the use
cases that you know there are common functionalities like whenever there is a common functionalities
which exist in the multiple objects one thing you can do is that this is something i'll introduce
a new key new way of saying a class is that you know this class is called as a parent class
okay or super class let's say i'll write down the things here parent class because there is
a child class now what does child class do i'll talk about that let's say i have a class student
right i use that a extends person now whenever i say that i'm extending a person it means that
i'm trying to inherit all the properties and functions which are present in parent class into
the child class now here let's say other than this name age let's say you have anyway student
will have its own name other than this he'll also have his age but let's say you also have a grade
in which class he's studying if you want to play around with this syntax and if you want to pass
on this values onto the top level i'll talk about this syntax case a second just let me code it down
and let's say a student will also have a method called study
inside the study let's say
i write down
this
so
now so what i just did here is that i say that hey there is over there may be a class which needs
still you know same variables i don't want to declare these two variables here again and there
can be a number of methods which are present which i want to reuse may not be declaring it okay such
as that hey a student can also create a person will also be doing something great every person
will create it okay so if you want to do that way and if you have specific methods you can add
it in the child now this particular student class is called as a child class okay so because
there is something we are extending we are extending parent like we are the children
of our parents whatever by default our parents has will be available for us but by default whatever
we has will not be available for the parents it's just is this clear guys why call name
age again in the student i'll come to that okay now
okay now if you see it here what what we are doing it like let's say now if i try to create a
student let's say firstly what we'll do is that we'll create a person object
let's say constant person equal to new person and let's say again i use
john and let's say his age is 26 okay and let's say i create a student object
student equal to new student now let's say student is what name we can let's say we'll
say use some bit let's say some bit is 24 or 25 and let's say his grade is maybe some 10th grade
okay now what i just stated here what's just happening let's say if i go through the flow
what just happens whenever i'm trying to create this object student object now whenever this
particular object is created the first function which gets executed is this constructor function
inside this constructor function since we are passing name and age and name and age are not
initialized here but they are initialized here in the parent class how you can call the parent
class from the child classes using the super keyword once you call the super keyword you are
actually going to this constructor and you know assigning values of name and age okay and creating
that student object along with grade okay let me show you this step by step in the debugging mode
let's say i have this thing
cd classes javascript
class 22
say node class hyphen three dot j s now let's say i call it here i call it here i put it here
okay let's try execute this one now if you see it here the first call now it is coming from the
person object now if you see whenever this call is getting executed this constructor if you see
this call is getting executed this constructor if you see age and name john and age is being
passed and that will be initialized okay this person or now this is having you know once this
name is assigned in this object which our object is created you can see that value is getting
updated here okay now the second function which line number 26 is executing student one now if
you see there are three variables that we initialize name age and grade when we pass these three things
once we are passing this now inside the super we are calling something like if you see what this
will happen once i click apply it is going inside the parent function do you see this like it went
into the person function where it is initializing age and name let's say if i go and initialize
okay now once i reach back here in this object both name age are initialized and the grade
will be upgraded is this clear guys how this is working super is generally is trying to interact
uh with the parent constructor where it is load initializing all the variables
and this phenomenon how this particular phenomenon how this is working is called as
inheritance the concept of inheritance is this simple that you are trying to get something from
parent and that is being leveraged by the children okay so then there is another
concept that i want to talk about is let's say there's something like static have you heard
those words static earlier anytime the word static i see three people uh guys can we define
it in your own terms what static is
i see four people can you guys define what static is can be used by others it won't change
okay guys uh let me explain it but before that i'll try to write one function okay let me do
what i'll do that in in the parent class itself i'll add a one new static function
okay saying that compare ages inside this i'll take two objects
of person one let's say person one and percent let's say here what i'll do is that i'm just
comparing it now what i'll compare let's say person one dot h if it is greater than percent two dot h
then i'll say that simply is that return uh string that person one dot name
is older than percent two dot name else if
this is the true then return
one person one is younger
else
return
person one is and
percent two are of same age okay so i hope this generally this method is i hope you got this
method what that static method is talking about just comparing the two persons with their ages
and whatever condition is satisfying will return that particular uh you know string now what the
static is we say that static whatever method is initially you know uh before any method that you
put it in the class if you are adding something like static keyword it means that this this
particular function belongs to the class but not to the object i'm repeating it again whenever you
have any functions or methods declared inside a class if there is something a static keyword
added before a method it means that this particular method belongs to the class but not to the object
did anyone understand the sentence
no right now i'll tell you now let's say now let's say even even without
even without you even without creating an object let's say now if i want to let's say that i'll
just say let's say i have two objects say person and person two i say that say this is a person
object i have say myself and let's say my age is 28 okay now i have this thing so one thing i have
to do it here is that let's say whatever i'm passing i should be passing in number format not
in the string okay now if i want to compare both the things if i want to compare both the things
right i don't need to use this object like these are the objects right person one and person two
are storing objects i don't need to do like person dot compare ages i can still do this but the
what it gives the static what it gives abilities like i can use directly person
class i'm using a class name here this class flash start compare ages if you see this method
i'm able to call this method directly and i can pass both the functions you see person person
too let's say if i try to console this log if you see john is younger than what some it says
now this thing got executed this method is executed on the class itself we didn't access it from the
object now if you remember do you do you by default anytime do you think that hey you can
do that some function dot because we so as we say that you know by default this class is a function
you know this do you remember by any chance if you remember can we do like function dot any method
can we do this way whatever we have done it just now
so are you are you able to understand what the static is firstly did you understand the static
if not give me a thumbs down okay i see three people cool now it is repeating it again guys
what i mean to say that now let's say if i do console dot log
person dot name let me try to execute this one
okay now what i when i do this person dot name what it what is the output that i get
the whole person do you see this even if i do
person dot age and i try to execute it it says that undefined
okay now what is happening here what is happening here let me show you again copying this one
uh putting it in the
let's say what is uh putting it here i created this one let's just see in the terminal okay
i created person constructor with this name name and age and a static method now once i initialize
this one if i try to say that person dot name okay is giving me directly a sting call person
where we didn't have initialized it yet but if i again go and do person dot age it gives me undefined
so by default what it says if you if you see this keyword name is actually uh like you know
present in the prototype let's say if i do this person um if i try to console dot even it will
give that same thing uh person dot you see name and everything actually the
keyword name is getting from the you know library which is which is telling the like what is the
class name so it is returning what is the class name if i update this and also let's say person
random it will return me still person random like let's say if i go and paste it again refreshing
everything
let's say i still do that person random
so in general what i meant to say that i'm not able to access this way values i am not able to
access but when i'm doing it name from the library it is giving me that what what is the
name of this class just that but do you see this like if i try to do like uh person
random dot age it keeps me undefined so this whatever values are generally you know name and
age values right whatever are defined inside the constructor and outside the constructor all this
belongs to an object you can always access this parameters or update this parameters only when
you have an object now let's say if i create an object called a new of person random
okay inside this i pass on let's say my name
and let's say i say that 28 or then i say that age if you see this i'm able to access the age
so there's a difference whenever there are some methods there are some things that you are only
able to access using the objects whenever you create an object those things are all things
which are present in the constructor function and all the methods except static static can be
directly accessed accessed using the parent i mean direct class itself when you say that
let's say person random will be able to access always this particular method if you see compare
edges by default is available you can always call it and you can always execute it let's say i give
it age as 28 and let's say another object age of 29 okay i'm not passing the name let's say i pass
the name as x name as y okay y is younger than the x so this is the name of the object
younger than the x so this is what it gives i didn't use any object i didn't create any object
using new keyword but i'm able to access this compare ages so i hope you are able to understand
what this static does static method belongs to the fun class doesn't belong to the object
so you don't need to create a new keyword and object and then try to access it you can directly
do it and you can use it anywhere and it whenever the class is initialized this thing is attached
to it but these things are only attached to it when you are actually you know like object is created
okay so i hope uh the concept these concepts are clear guys like what is static
now and inheritance is also clear i'm uh we're not going completely into oops because this is
a really lessly i mean we don't really use or i don't think you will be tested in interviews based
on this concepts like our classes until unless until unless you are going with something written
in your profile like you are an angular developer because angular uses class-based syntax this they
are still for constructor-based syntax they are still creating an object and playing around with
that but they write it in that in those terms when it comes to react next.js view or any popular
framework you use they all use a functional based syntaxes okay i hope this thing is clear guys
now so uh
guys uh do you need a break or should i continue because there's only one topic left which i have
to take it uh so then we can end the class because this is not a huge concept okay sure
says break there's anyone needs a break or can i continue give me thumbs up for the continue give
me thumbs thumbs down for the break uh guys i need some votes and to understand like i see that people
are asking me to continue okay so hold on for half an hour uh like maybe 20 minutes 25 minutes
we are done with uh today's content okay so i'll try to explain the kind okay now then let's say
now i have one of the use case that i want to build okay let me do a you know class four
dot js now inside this class four dot js what i have to want to do is
if i want to replicate let's say inheritance if you see this logic like student is extending parent
we say that this sound this thing this is same as like function constructor function but how can
we do this how can we do this let's explore this one how can we do this okay let's say i go and
write function let's say instead of person random i'll create a person
again uh same thing uh this is pretty uh naive that this function that we are rewriting again
and again let's say this is the same thing and once this is done we also have this greet
now this greet is added outside the person so if i want to replicate that one i'll do something
like person dot prototype dot greet inside this great i'll create a function and i'll call it
let's console dot log
okay so this is what we replicated now one thing i'll leave it to you is like how can you add a
static method i'll show you the hint like how the static works but you have to figure it out
okay and it will take only one minute for you guys to guess it i'll show it in real time how
this works okay but uh but do you understand that how did i replicate this one this particular
person class other than the static method if i close it down this thing other than this this
these parts are clear right how i'm able to convert a class base into functional component
functional constructor function guys uh quick thumbs up thumbs down if you are able to understand
this one they're not okay great now then there is a something called let's say student let's say
let's create this function student it will have a name age and grid cool it has these things now
inside this i'll have something like this dot grade and great i am not still calling name in
h but how we would handle it here can you guys think of it like what could be the use case
how can we handle this
now i'll write something which i'll explain it in the next class okay let's say i call something
like person dot call inside this call i'll pass on something values let's say i pass on
this keyword i say that i'm passing on this object i'm passing on name and each now firstly
in next class i'll come back and explain this line but understand the thing that i'm just
replicating the super behavior okay like i'm calling the parent level now once i do this i
have this something like study let's say i have to replicate this study student dot proto type
dot study
inside this function let's say i have it this then i try to console log the same thing
okay once i do this i have done it now that's all okay we have created student guys is this
clear student how the student is replicating this particular class one final thumbs up great now
but we miss something like hey how are you extending this person right how we are extending this
person how we are able to connect both of those classes or both of these functions isn't it
okay how we can do this is that let's say since this is an inheritance concept i'll say that
student dot prototype student prototype i mean student is inheriting from its parent now which
parent is that i will define such that object dot create student dot prototype sorry person dot
no i'll talk on this what what is this actually doing okay we are saying that there is something
which is extending parent okay we have to say that there is something which is you know
should have access now if you see it what i exactly meant on this sentence what i exactly
meant on this sentence is that if you see on person prototype i added greet method right if
i need greet method inside the student also the student object should have access to this grid
now how can i have it access i say that hey whatever in student prototype object is there
in that object assign all the methods which are present in person prototype
is this clear guys what this line is doing again i'll repeat it is that i want now using this call
function i am able to assign all the variables that is fine i'm updating all the variables i'm
getting the touch what about the function greet which is present inside the class like this how
i'm able to access this greet method using student object in order to do that he's what
we are saying that in student prototype will have all the methods which are present in persons
prototype object okay using the syntax we'll be able to link those both those objects now let's
say if i try to create const person same thing let's say i try to copy it from here and i try
to show you guys okay now firstly i'll copy the whole content and i'll try to execute it here
okay let's let me before executing again i'm showing you guys is that there's a one function
constructor with these two variables and there's a one method which is added here
into its prototype then there's a student which is trying to interact with its parent
we are calling this call method i'll explain how this call works in next class but also student
will also have its in prototype there's something function called study then we are linking both
such that hey in the inside student object this should be able to access person we are this is
how we are linking it okay now let's say i cool i execute this one okay person is already declared
uh let me go into incognito mode new window let's say i inspected console clean it up
yeah this is working fine now but now let's say what is happening here
it's an access person now if you see i'm able to access all the values that i need
john h fine what if i want to greet it
okay i'm getting greeting from the john what if i want to access student
student if i'm still able to access all the values let's say i will print a grade once
just to replicate it that i have grade also if student want to greet it let's say greet
do you see this greeting from some bit it says because we initialize students with a some bit
okay also student want to study
uh just a second we have a study function this dot name this dot grade all great student
all great student dot study
let's say i go it here inside this person object greet
i have it
it but there is something is missing is that okay now guys can you figure out why study is
not available here why study is not available if i just update it from here to this line
these things will be working why do you think i've assigned i updated its whole prototype
but i want to add in prototype like new function right key value pair that's where it's missing
let me try to show it again uh sorry for moving speed uh let's say if i go for a student
now if i try to print student
expand this one expand this person do you see study is available now okay let's say
uh i go back i try to say the student not study
okay student dot greet
okay uh
do you see both things are working on student student is able to access its own method also
it is able to access parent class method parent constructor function method is this clear guys
actually how this i'm able to convert from a class to the functional programming firstly
just want to know give me one thumbs up thumbs down okay i want to explain few more things uh
now i want to go into one one of the topic like if this thing is clear i want to talk on something
like prototype and prototypical chain okay one concept like people generally you know
fear of that's not a difficult concept at all okay uh okay what is prototype
and prototypical chain
okay basic thing now if you have seen i've shown you with the functions firstly i've shown you with
the functions now let's say if i create an array const array let's say i have one two three
okay i've created an array now if i do array dot length or last index
where do you think i'm able to get this methods from
where do you think these methods are available from array dot for each method or filter method
or whatever map functions we learned right whatever things we have learned
where do you think these are all are coming from any idea guys
these are coming from again it's prototype now on based on the data type if you see if i expand it
this is array is actually what uh you know some bit declared it in his project if i'm trying to
console log i'm able to console log that one but here do you see that hey i'm having a prototype
attached to it like array type of prototype yes can you see this there's a prototype available
in array also expand this now if you expand this do you see concat entries fill filter find index
last index flat right join keys map push and pop reduce all these higher order functions
whichever are there are available in its prototype what what can you say all the library
for each and every data type or each and every data structure that you see in javascript
are accessed using this prototype so we can say that in each and every each and every data type
has an object attached to it
so whenever you create an array or function or class or object or set
or map anything you create whatever you create in js an object is attached that object is called
as prototype inside this prototype you will have all the methods now imagine even when someone has
declared an array data structure in the javascript let's say they might have written something like
this one right function dot array whatever it is there okay now on array dot prototype they added
length what this length should do right then they added all simultaneous method this was
a syntax that was done so by default array has an prototype which has all the library methods
right is this example clear guys what prototype is every thing that you create in javascript there
will be an object attached to it through which it is inheriting all the uh you know libraries
methods supporting methods or the values that you see okay uh is this point clear guys
uh guys if you didn't understand you can give me thumbs down right away i'll try to
re-explain it we'll take a deep breath we'll come back and we understand it
if you're not able to understand give me thumbs down cool now let's say
okay let's say uh what i'm doing is that i'll create an object let's say object
okay uh i think we have this already okay i created this object let's say
okay let's say i have an object in the memory i try to access this object
okay
okay let's say i have this uh okay in the memory i have object now inside this object i should be
able to access this first name that is fine because we declared it but if i try to print
this object right if you see inside this object along with the first name there is something
attached is something called prototype object this what is the data type of this object
again they say that this it's an object type only and that object name is called prototype
this is a key the key is called prototype okay now even if i go and say that array one
and again i have one two three okay i print it now if i try to print array one now if you see
inside this whatever we have defined it's zero index first and second index it is there length
is there but do you see here even if i define object even if i define an array there is an
prototype object is attached always let's say i create a function now function test
console dot log uh let's say i did something random if i die to do test okay
it is not showing but if i so if you see this i try to print prototype do you see this there
are prototype object attached to the function also is this point clear that you create an array
is this point clear that you create an array object or anything there is an object that is
attached with the key value name as prototype you can always access this key prototype object
using object dot prototype so every time you create anything there is an object attached to the
like the the variable name that you are creating with and that you can access that extra object
that is created using dot operator now all the libraries that you see in array or object right
methods that you see like whatever methods we have learned on array how they are how we are able to
access it if you prefer other languages used to import that whole library in the file right
do you remember that that you import array array least properties or we can say that object class
is a default i'll come to that up now i'll come to that but understand that first level is that
you are having the library which is all available okay in java you used to import all like a library
hole on a top from the java.util right in a same way here we are not importing it by default all
these methods are loaded in the prototype if you see first level prototype is array.prototype you
have all these methods which are available on array now if you see on this prototype also there
is something like prototype available again this is something like constructor has own properties
prototype is local string so if i try to do something like let's say array one dot prototype
okay
okay now if you see array one has this one like underscore underscore proto now if i do it again
underscore underscore proto if you see this one what underscore underscore proto does is like
whenever you want to attach value right whenever you want to attach anything value to it like we
are just doing in the function right what we were doing here in the function whenever you want to
attach or update this thing you have to use this keyword called prototype but when you want to
access and see it you have to use something called as like like pro underscore underscore
proto that gives you a lookup like you can search using that thing or understand that thing using
now let's understand this case with a simple thing firstly array one is an array data structure
where if i try to do something like underscore proto what it is giving it is giving me all the
methods if you see it's an array of methods inside that array of methods we have all having the
methods related to an array but if i go and do it array one dot underscore underscore proto
again i do on this underscore underscore proto then i'm able to access still those methods
and this method if you see constructor has own property property and everything now let's say
again i have an object right object that i created if you see that with first name
if i try to access its proto do you see this its proto and array one proto is same firstly
guys are you able to see this these methods are same in object and array now what it says is that
you know what happens in the chain what happens in the chain is let's say there is any library
like if you see when we created first simple when we created simple person right when we created
simple person and if we wanted to add anything method we added on its prototype right prototype
we added like there should be a greet function now after this green on this function great function
whenever you create a function we saw we have seen that there is another prototype added
which is to the function level okay so in the end right if you go on building any data structure
like array array will have its own prototype which will support all the methods like same as
in a person object is agreed so it will have concat index of and all those methods like length
is a variable so you can access without a prototype so all these things will be there
now after this there will be another prototype so this last ending prototype right in the chain
whichever thing is there in the chain it goes on to you know root prototype is object type
when you create an object let's say when you whenever you create an object in js
like first name or anything
let's say you created this whatever object dot proto underscore underscore proto
is there no that is our end that's the end prototype end object like because if you see
there is something like oh if you go for array right how it will be it will be like okay whatever
values you are there these values are there and then you have prototype inside this prototype you
will have some list of methods after that list of method again you will have another prototype
and this prototype is actually having a list of methods which are same as object dot prototype
so we can say that this is a chain which is forming firstly you will have whatever
values to describe then supporting library which is defined then you will have a object
based library one thing you can do is like you can also access like this level of chaining
like let's say if i want to access list whatever things are there in array one if you see inside
array one you have this like has own property or anything let's say if i do array one dot has
own property okay and it seeks that whether it has anything what i'm doing in array one i'm checking
whether there is a value one available let's say if you see it here i'm having true let's say i try
to reuse this one as of four if you say it is returning false so this method is not actually
belonging to array because we don't learn it on array because this is coming from object level
prototype because object also provides you something two string now where this two string
is coming from let's say if i convert this array one dot two string okay whenever i call this
method you see it converted this array into two string this is coming from object so can i say
that everything in javascript is actually an object because through the prototype chain
everything is having an access to that object object prototype
yes are you able to follow up with the sentence
so everything in javascript by default is is an object because anything that you create anything
that you create of you know anything that you create in the end when you go at the last you'll
have object prototype available attached to it on everything and mostly for everything you will be
able to apply these methods okay like has own property constructor properties enable local string
okay you'll be value of you'll be able to see all of them you can apply to them okay so i hope
this prototype chain is also clear like how this chaining happens and how can you access the methods
inside the chain because i have seen you with a real time example when you created this particular
thing okay if you see if i try to replicate this example right how this thing worked how this thing
how this thing worked how this thing worked okay let's say i try to show you like let's say i have
an exiled raw so i use this one let's say i have this one and
let's say this is a person inside person if you see what we are initializing variables name and age
okay cool
let's say we are having values here name and age that's done but when i create a prototype
let's say i'm creating a prototype here
okay let's say this is a another prototype
now how did i access created this one i said that person.prototype add a new method inside
this called as greet right if you see this this is the same thing that i did
next level what i did i went on to create something like person
i went on to create something like student then on the student i added like
grade name age grade right i had grade name and age i'll explain in next class when i explain
call function but other than that thing we also created a prototype for this one
okay now what i did here in this next step was i connected these two functions
how did i connect these functions what i just said there is that hey whatever student.prototype
is there now you know attach it with something called person.prototype
is this clear what actually happened in this line when i did this
also what i did i said that hey can you do one thing or this so even though this is a prototype
also add one more method here which is study
so that whenever i do something like let's say i know after this what whatever i am trying to
whatever i am trying to access it let's say i since this since i have done this chain
i can say that i if i need to access person dot greet i will be able to access because on person
prototype i'm having a greet if i have to do person dot study i won't be able to access it
because on person dot prototype i don't have study okay it is present on student.prototype
this won't work this will give undefined but on student i can say that student dot greet it will
work because we can append it this one like on this more updated the whole object we actually
sent all of assigned new object person and also student dot study will also work
is this clear guys how this is working
guys is this clear now let's let me show you one more thing
let me show you one more thing once i copy and paste this one right let me go back here
one thing i want to show you is that again i'll show you one chain system
now let's say i go to the person this is a function right that we created let's say person random
if you see i'm having this person random if i try to let's say access its prototype
what is the default object attached in order to access i can do underscore
underscore proto right if you see this is a function native it says but if i go and do again
underscore underscore proto do you see this by default end goal for the function is also
okay i'll come to that one i'm sure but do you understand this again for this function also
whatever we created this same thing is happening like again the root level protein in the chain
the root level is object itself okay i hope this chaining and what is the keyword called proto
and when to use prototype when to use underscore underscore proto that thing is clear
whenever you want to attach something is prototype you have to use prototype keyword if you want to
read and understand the content of it you have to use underscore underscore proto underscore
underscore okay now apart from this so muneshwara has a doubt that earlier we were adding it this
one on the top why didn't it worked it now okay let's say what happened here now let's say i have
let me explain an example what just happened let's say i have an const object i say that
you know it has something first name let's say last name
let's say smith okay and a created object one okay it has something like first name
let's say john now if i want to update it if i want to update merge both of them right if
i want to update both of them one thing i can always uh you know uh okay
uh okay okay i have to i'm picking up wrong example but i will just show what i did it
now let's say when i was having this thing
on the student dot prototype let's say on the student dot
i attached new method called steady
okay
this is something we did it but on this line i updated whole prototype object
using assignment operator
okay and we lost
steady are you able to understand that we lost that completely so i said that hey i'll only i
need to only attach a new new key q key value pair into the object right so i've just moved
below then it will work
so i guess uh hope everyone got this understanding and i just want to know guys
did you understand internals like how this object-oriented programming actually works
in javascript because there is nothing as such object-oriented uh exists in javascript it's
it's just a constructor function and one thing i left it for you is that let's say
let's say this one right how this static method is created i didn't create in the class four
but i'll just show it to you how that works let's say if i try to print this person and
since it's printing the whole class let's say i do that person dot
under underscore proto once i do this it is printing me native still but when i say guys
just think of this thing when i say that you know something belongs to a class it doesn't
belong to its prototype isn't it isn't it same as this dot compare edges
do you think isn't it same as this one
this both things if i write static and i declare outside or else i declare it inside the constructor
itself just think of it whether this is same or how do you can create constructor i'll explain
in the next class how can you i hope you will debug and come back how can you create a static
how can you create a static method in this format okay debug and come back and let me
know how can you handle this one in the next class so guys the content is that i said today
because we wanted to understand classes objects and you know behind the scene what happens and
prototype prototype chain hope you all got the concepts right i'll i'll i'll would say that hey
you want to go through pick up your any material that you have on this concepts go through it if
you face any understanding challenge do let me know i'll be there i'll try to help you out
understand things and figure it out is that fine guys so with this i want to start the doubt
session and if you have doubts placed yeah i'll i'll give you that muneshwara i'll just say that
you know go for by default you know javascript info firstly read about something called prototype
or inheritance and prototype you will be able to understand like you know then you have something
like class based things okay simple things you this two uh you know chapters okay these two
chapters eighth and ninth chapter i'll ping you this one are we going to use this anytime in project
uh somebody i hardly used it in my experience i never used uh i mean i did coding on angular
angular 2 uh i used class based uh syntaxes up to extent but if i'm going on react profile i don't
expect someone asking me classes but i can be asked something on prototype and prototypal
inheritance reason behind because prototypal inheritance is how the inheritance works in
javascript behind the scenes like how we are able to access methods on array or how we are able to
access methods on function or on object those concepts may be asked in interview uh more but
if you are going on react i expect this chapter to be covered but if you see this thing will be
specific to mostly angular specific okay
i hope you got that point so guys do you want me to attach this do you want me to attach this
okay let's say this example will be there
i'll just
let's say i'll keep it here itself for reference okay anytime if you want to
refer you can refer it i will push this code base and i'll start doubt session guys
and uh guys stick around for five minutes uh i want to talk about the contest so that everyone
is prepared okay i i want everyone to revise the you know the code that we have done with respect
to dom with respect to the uh debouncing throttling the images that i have shared the
differences you got it try to write your own one one set of example uh revise the dom concepts how
things are going just go through the notes once or twice and then try to attempt the contest okay
before that don't go directly with the blind just check on the notes and then you will be i will be
i would believe that you are confident confident enough because i have received answers from each
and everyone you were confident about when you were answering me all the things related to dom
i believe you all people will go and clear that context in case you have any doubts you're not
able to understand anyways i'm here we will discuss post contest okay but i want everyone
out of 30 people who are joining the classes please attempt go and attempt the contest
hopefully and let me know how how it was in the next class uh mostly it will be mcq promote but
there might be one two coding questions maybe on rebouncing and throttling so you can expect
that or a small js based questions uh but it will be pretty much simple as far as i know because
it's our beginner batch right so it will be straightforward questions but anyways i contest
is one of the way to test it but i want you guys to be prepared be understanding the dom
and revising because we will be moving fast forward with you know with more speed uh with
more depth in js as you see now i've covered the classes in a one hour and i say that it's
not that much useful i say that everything is built using again functional constructors itself
constructor function itself how do you deal it and what are the how do you connect with them right
so all those things will be coming up i hope but you keep revising the concepts and come back
leverage the weekend guys as much as possible clean the clear up all the assignment problems
whatever you have seen percentage dropping uh maybe i see that there are 20 or 25 people who
are consistent but there are four or five people who are facing challenge and getting time figure
it out guys uh but if you need anything from my side do let me know i'll try to help you out okay
so uh it was a big monologue guys
but uh just want to go back know that did you understand the today's concept
was it uh good to know internals how this thing works right because there is nothing new wheel
invented guys the year 16 syntax team didn't do anything new they just converted the past this
code converted into something existing thing okay in that existing concept also i taught you one is
functional constructor function which you learned in last class and then there is something called
prototypal chain okay i hope you go through this two chapters eight and nine chapters out of this
javascript info we'll be picking up one by one guys if you see one by one when i say one by one
what all we have covered we have covered objects like we have covered optional chaining uh
constructor function we have covered this uh coding qualities we covered debugging in
browser right poly fields will come to it but if you see um if you go and say this right all
these things we will be count anyways we'll be covering it one by one if you feel i haven't
covered anything do let me know there are a few library methods like map and set this thing we
can cover it anytime if you want it not a big deal okay but it's not part of curriculum but i'll
i can cover it as if you need it in js terms if you read it you'll get it if you don't i'd let
me know okay destructuring we covered how can you destructure things right but it's just that you
go and explore this one you will get to know okay modules and everything will come to when you
exports and export how they work we'll come to that promises this thing is going to be all
async class where we'll cover this whole this thing in three classes it will take three classes
to understand promises and async await it is time taking one then i hope but one of the thing
that you should be sure about is that this one browser documents interface this chapter inside
the javascript info will have everything related to dom how dom is prepared what is happening
behind the scenes and everything okay uh bubbling and capturing event delegation right this thing
we have covered mouse events we have covered one of the event uh tricky event is how do you build
drag and drop like if you want to upload a file how do you build it at drag and drop
you can explore this then we have understood form like how do you focus on a form because we have
built right that otp example where you focus was changing from one button to one form element to
the other right then we covered what is difference between async and differ okay so most of the
concepts we have covered but i would urge you again go and read this dom uh browser level
events because this is something covered and i don't want you to say that hey we don't know
some concept or anything it would be good for you if you go and read through this one okay
then there is additional uh i'll i'll i'll tell you when to when you need to go through this one but
you know this one particular thing right this particular thing is really helpful this site
is good for revision quick revision if you want to do it in time in theoretical ways they also
have an example like how this thing works like if you see one of the example for the browser events
right if you see they'll see uh click mouse down mouse move mouse over right key down event submit
focus transition so all those on top level they give how how do you handle these things and how
this works uh leverage this site learn this much as much as possible right for html and css there
was a different site that you have to prefer which is built by google
yeah web dev so if you go to web dev right you it's really great site to understand both
html and css leverage web dev uh for understanding this one like if i go back
because this thing will not only give the knowledge on html css but down the lane
this will also give you understanding you know core web vitals which is actually you know how
do you test the performance of your application how do you optimize it all those things because
this thing uh is it's a something that i i still keep reading because i still figure out how you
can work on this because these are the bigger chapters uh reducing load uh largest content
full paint uh you know the loading first time how how long time it takes to initially paint
that first page and render it okay this is bit advanced level core web vitals but this is also
one of the great websites to explore i'll give you this thing i refer to these two basic websites
guys whenever i want to revise anything related to core fundamentals web dev and javascript info
is our best site as per my knowledge if you have anything it's really great all the github's
profiles gives you like another thing for machine coding as i shared you the urls for the machine
coding go through them and for react when we go for react i'll share you the link actually
anything else guys uh now there's a one question that initially i had it uh from kabir kabir do
you understand what was your question's answer actually how does it work
just checking with the kabir are you there in your are you there in the class
uh he dropped
let's say i've marked it as answered because the question was same thing as prototype
how different is nextjs
uh firstly
what is nextjs what do you think nextjs amit
what is nextjs according to you no idea at all okay no worries i'll tell you i'll give
you just context about it don't want to talk it in depth at paypal we are using its beta version
we are exploring whether to use it or not
you know uh let me have a some water speaking for two
there were two sort of architectures right there were two sort of architectures which
was in discussion for the long time so client and server
right when it comes to ui as i told earlier like when it goes for java right there was
something like j2 double e they also in j2 they also gave an ability to build html
write js and css inside the java code itself then they use what they used to do is right on
on client itself there was no react there was no html css js written on the browser they were
used to throw from server itself all the all the files there was no web layer in between but later
on what it is that in order to build newer better syntaxes the world started building
the client side applications are separately and in order to better optimize this thing
there have been libraries and frameworks many things came into you know into the world
now when this happened right so people started saying that hey java will handle only backend
logic let's decouple both client and service layer will decouple we want this code to exist
here this code to exist here related to browser will exist in different component related to
server side will rely on different component so what then what happened is like we built html
css js in the front end component along with this to optimize it we had frameworks like react
angular and view in order to fasten the work now what happened with this thing all
all is that i made i started now if i need a data i need a data or images or big things again i
started communicating with this backend i'm still fetching the data right i'm still fetching the
data and whenever i'm fetching the data i can see in the browser network tab all the api calls
and i'm also able to see the ip address of a system where my calls are going though this ip
address will be reflecting your router ip address but we are able to see all the api calls being done
and it is comparatively slower they say that you are trying to fetch the data now
then two things arised firstly older framework when they were directly rendering
they used to say something called a server-side rendering
when i say server-side rendering what i mean to say that hey i'll completely build all the merge
all of them i'll build everything i'll serve browser only html
html i'll give browser directly html it only need to pass html and work is done
but here what we are doing on once it is passing is done we are loading the js
joe's code is executed we are making api call we are getting json data and we are building it
this sort of architecture is called client-side rendering
so is this clear what is client-side rendering versus server-side rendering first point
now when this next js came right when this next js came they introduced
server-side rendering concept
so
such that you hide all api calls from network tab
and prefetch
prefetch required data from server
so
and load as much as possible
static files on browser
this is how i understand so what next js used to provide initially was server-side rendering
components they they they leveraged react they built again they went back into the voltage they
say that hey we'll make an api call behind the scenes we'll make it fast and we'll club
everything on the server of this react next js itself and we'll give it browser only html so
that browser doesn't take the headache this is clear what next js used to do that used to build
server-side rendering components later on later on some people still leverage client-side rendering
also on next js so next js was actually empowering react empowering react with few more concepts
built along with it there was router examples and everything i'll tell you in the depth but
this is on a top level what what was happening behind the scenes why people started picking up
next js next js solved two problems one is routing one is ssr ssr is one of the most you know
something new that people got attracted always people like something new and they find the
reasons to use it okay so this is they leverage both of the same server-side rendering again
ssr is server-side rendering okay server-side rendering not routing i would say okay now
later on yeah these are the two things they kept on improving few more things i have not
burst with latest next js because most of the companies still write
when i when you go for enterprise level like really enterprise level
when i say enterprise like consider my workplace paypal we still are on react
we have our own framework called kraken i cannot talk more on this kraken
let me see it is open source or not only then i can talk on it
okay
kraken
yeah kraken js this is there now
now
no so we have built our yeah we have built our own framework called it's a murn stack
framework full stack on for the client side web web layer where we have all the types of things
that we need we we are using kraken we are leveraging ssr and csr client side and server
side rendering both we have solutions for all the predefined as for our authentication there
but leveraging next j's i we don't think having much of a opportunity so many teams are not
spending time towards it because the code bases are huge we don't have time to work on it
okay so you can study about kraken if you want to study it's exposed right you'll see that there's
a next j's i mean note j's code written you will be able to understand all these things once we
learn node j's how tough are paypal interviews
i don't know what past but in future they are going to be more tougher because you know we
are working on getting lean if you see we are having a tough time when it comes to because
we are having competition from stripe and apple pay and some companies so there's too much things
going inside and we are working on tightening things so hiring will be less important in terms
of paypal and we will be having much more difficult things earlier i would say it was
like at microsoft level and amazon these all things are less on the one level
paypal and everything for for roles of sd2 and abo okay because here at paypal sd2 and sd3 is
equal to like lower sd3 and sd2 is equal to sd2 of microsoft and you know sd2 of
amazon whereas mts1 which we call it as a staff level engineer which is equivalent to senior
software engineer high level and sd3 of amazon so depending upon the role you are viewing
it is going to be tougher in future that's what's my understanding because we were even given
guidance i used to take some interviews i mean i've interviewed only for the college level
college freshers like who are for hiring interns and for paypal so i didn't get a chance to you
know for fts to interview fts because hiring has been really less okay and our decks have been not
yet supported okay guys so it's not good to talk about more personal internal things but i'll
restrain from talking about them somewhere
but if someone needs referral as i told if there are openings i would refer it once end of the
curriculum right if they are still keeping in touch they're coming to class and they're doing
really great if i feel them i will talk to the managers and you know try to get an interview
set up if there are decks opening okay
great guys then we will end the session today here hope you got to learn explore things and
you liked it let's let's meet on tuesday hope you do the assignment problems and you know
solve the things thanks ambed you've been really progressing great i hope everyone also try to you
know build applications like you are doing it you know really great kudos to your efforts i hope
i'm always bookmarking your applications and build one portfolio project where you link all
the projects that you're building through the curriculum okay and notice i see other people
if you're not able to find time we'll figure it out someday we'll sit together and build it
even after the batch ends i'll be anyways available on the whatsapp you can ping me on
okay so with that good night see you enjoy your weekend rock the contest let's meet back and
explore some of the higher order functions and learn more things so guys bye bye take care
good night guys
you